this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
sea radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
hello everyone this is Priyanka Priyanka
ragran for software engineering radio
and today my guest is Ross Anderson and
we'll be discussing software
obsolescence Professor Ross Anderson is
a professor of security engineering at
the department of computer science and
engineering at the University of
Cambridge where he's a part of the
University's security group he's also
professor of security engineering at the
University of Edinburgh
he's an author of the book called
security engineering a guide to building
Dependable systems and his areas of
Interest are security dependability and
Technology policy I wanted to have him
on the show to discuss software
obsolescence after a very engaging
conversation at his office at Cambridge
University and welcome to the show thank
you but I see radio we've done a few
shows on technical debt managing
software supply chain attacks a show on
software archiving but you never done a
full show on obsolescence and the reason
I wanted to do it was because of fact
that it's hitting everyone now and or
very little attention is actually being
paid to it so let's just start right
from the top for our listeners would you
be able to explain what is obsolescence
or end of software life well as time
goes on people add new features to
software the software features interact
you end up getting dependability issues
you end up getting security
vulnerabilities and so the software has
to be upgraded and of course no piece of
software lives on its own nowadays the
artifacts with which we interact tend to
you know have millions of lines of code
they talk to servers the servers talk to
apps there's a whole ecosystem at every
node
and so whenever you get a new
version of iOS or Android or Linux or
whatever coming out that has
implications that Ripple through the
whole ecosystem similarly
when components such as webkit get
upgraded that can Ripple through many
other parts of the system and now we're
making things still more complicated by
bringing in new types of components in
the form of machine learning models
which will be embedded Here There and
Everywhere
and coordinating
the disclosure of vulnerabilities the
upgrade to patch vulnerabilities the
upgrades that are necessary for
dependability is becoming an Ever more
complex task
how this reflects in real life is that
you may be tempted to go and buy a
fridge for a bit more money because it's
advertised as a smart fridge and it
talks to Wi-Fi and then two years later
you find that the manufacturer doesn't
maintain the server anymore and it turns
into a frosty brick so we find that
artifacts that used to be good for 10
years or 20 years or 30 years
suddenly become dysfunctional because
the software that was built into them to
support complex business models fills
far before the underlying Hardware does
and this is about to be a serious
problem for example with cars on the one
hand it's great that we move to electric
cars because an electric power train has
got maybe a hundred components instead
of the 2000 components in an internal
combustion engine powertrain so you
don't need to hire as many car mechanics
but there's so much more software that
you have to hire lots of software
Engineers to pick up the maintenance
burden that has not been eliminated but
merely shifted this is going to have all
sorts of political and economic effects
worldwide it's great for India because
there will be lots and lots of jobs for
software maintenance engineers
with the big tech companies in India and
in many new startups it's perhaps less
good for employment or skilled mechanics
in North America and Western Europe and
over the next 20 years all these
implications are going to be working
their way through the system
and it's up to us as technologists to
try and understand what's going on to
try and figure out how we can make
better tools to make software last
longer to figure out how we can perhaps
redesign institutions so that we can do
coordinated disclosure of
vulnerabilities better there's a whole
lot of pieces to solving this problem I
think like you rightly said it's a maze
and there's a there's a lot of things
that need to be tied up and maintained
so one of the questions I wanted to ask
you picking up from that is when a
software gets obsolete does that mean
nothing works or can it still be used
with risks and if you could just maybe
talk a little bit about the risks
because there's a case where you can
actually work on things which are
obsolete but then of course there's a
lot of risks Associated risks well the
question is whether the the artifact
that you're trying to maintain was
designed so that it would have a known
death date or whether it would merely
degrade
for example my wife had a Lexus that was
almost 20 years old which we
got rid of last year and replaced with a
new car but for all the time that she
owned it we couldn't use the GPS because
the GPS the navigation and that display
was of a generation that was designed 25
years ago
and it had a strange pop-up screen that
would show the moving map display which
still popped up annoyingly in the
dashboard but it depended entirely on
getting a new DVD every year from Lexus
with a new updated map of the whole
world in it and Lexus stops applying
that about 10 years ago
so here's a car with a subsystem that
was completely non-functional so how you
you replace that of course is you get a
clip and you clip your mobile phone onto
the air vent and you fire up Google Maps
or Apple Maps and you use that to
navigate instead there's going to be
more and more of that let me give you
another example we moved house recently
and the two owners previous owners of my
new house were both Gadget freaks and
the most recent owner was Authority was
a gadget freak he was not an engineer
and so he didn't understand how to do
maintenance and documentation
so my house is haunted right it's like
it's got a poltergeist in it because at
all times of the day and night there'll
suddenly be a quick click and if we're
under muscle starts up somewhere in the
house and I'm trying to figure out
what's on Earth is going on and so I go
to the electricity meter and I see that
this is drawing 270 watts and I figure
well you know what could that be and I
go around and I listen and tap the walls
and eventually
you know with much exploration than
patience I find out everything that's
happening and whether I want to turn
things off or maintain them or replace
them or whatever but this is our future
right it's not just about maintaining
software it's about maintaining all
these things that have got software in
them and all these things that have
things in them that have software in
them that somebody bought 14 years ago
because it seemed like a good idea at
the time
wow so this is really one of like the
negative impacts of to customers which
hits home I did listen to one of your
other podcasts and there was something
that you refer to as like turning on a
dumb switch and I think that what you
said is when the software on a phone or
a car is no longer supported we were
suggesting that you essentially like
take it off the internet and thus you
can make it more sustainable or
Dependable can you talk a little bit
about that move for the listeners here
well one of my interests has always been
technology for development you know my
wife is from Cape towns so I thought
she's of an Indian family and so I have
in-laws in both in India and Africa and
when we go to Africa we see that many of
the cars there
are 20 years old
because there are cars that had a first
life in
you know Britain or Singapore or Japan
and then when they were 10 years old
they were put on boats and they went to
Africa and they then lived for another
10 years
until they eventually fall to pieces
and there was a big question as cars get
software because you see in Western
Europe
you have to get your car pass a
roadworthiness test once a year you go
in and they test the brakes and the
software and they the lights and all the
50 stuff they check the tires now fairly
soon they're going to start checking
that the software has been upgraded
and this means that when the carve Ender
no longer provides software upgrades
the car presumably has to be exported
or scrapped now this is a real big deal
and we had a big fight in the European
Union and from 2016 to 2019 over how
long the car makers would have to
maintain the software and the car makers
Volkswagen and Mercedes and Peugeot and
so on said we only want to maintain
software for six years because we either
sell you a three-year lease on a news
car or a three-year lease on a new car
depending on how much money you have and
we don't want to maintain past the sixth
year because you know that's the
duration of our sales contracts and the
European Union eventually said no well
you've got a legal obligation to make
spare parts available for 10 years so
we're going to make you make software
available for 10 years too and it was
possible to push this through only
because of the emission Scandal which
weakened the political power of the car
companies now if this means that the
maximum life of a car in Europe in five
or ten years time will be 10 years
then this is an environmental disaster
because at present the average age of a
car when it's scrapped in Europe is 16
years
right so if that is reduced from 16
euros to 10 years what happens to all
these millions of 10 year old cars
do we export all of them to Africa
that's probably not the market for it
and in Africa how do people drive them
this is another problem if you go to
Kenya for example you find that most of
the cars on the roads in Kenya were
originally in Japan because that's how
the trade works and so there are people
in Kenya who are Specialists you know
who know how to read Japanese manuals
and things like that and to fix stuff up
how does how is this going to work out
once cars have got software in them that
become safety critical
this is something we have to start
thinking about now because if you reduce
the the life of cars by two-thirds you
have to bear in mind that the the total
life cycle carbon cost of a car is only
50 in the fuel it's fifty percent in
making the car
and so you've got a significant increase
in CO2 emissions if you scrap all cars
after 10 years
so this means that you have to make car
software in a way that is maintainable
and that's hard because the software in
the car typically comes from 40
different companies you know there'll be
this software in the brake controller
this in the engine controller this is in
the remote key entry system other
software and the controller that
operates the sliding roof
and maybe only three or three or four of
the most safety critical but they still
come from different companies and
testing them together you know the
integration test for safety is a complex
and expensive process who's going to do
that and so that brings me to another
question so in your research and your
experience do you have any data on the
lifespan of a software project how long
does it typically last well there has
been research on software project
management going back to the 1960s
because once IBM started selling large
mainframes at scale to many businesses
and Computing was no longer a craft
thing done by Specialists then people
started to notice that most software
projects were late and some were never
finished at all perhaps a third of big
software projects became disasters
and that was in companies in governments
typically two-thirds of large software
projects become disasters despite the
fact that civil servants are more
risk-averse than company managers and
people have been trying to understand
this now for all of my working life and
this is where the very idea of software
engineering comes from
the idea was coined by Brian Randall who
was then a young academic in Newcastle
University now he's very old he's in his
80s he's Emeritus professor
but his idea was that the techniques
that in Newcastle they used to build
ships could be applied to software if
you'd assertively top-down structure if
you started with a plan and you
organized things into you know laying
down the Keel making the ribs putting on
the plates putting in the engines
putting on the decks fitting out the
cabins then presumably you would be able
to scale up software the way you could
scale up shipbuilding and of course it
doesn't work that way because the bigger
a software project becomes the more the
complexity grows it's it's not something
that roses are there in more like all
their N squared and so in practice the
largest software artifacts that we
produce are not built but to grow them
you know things like Windows or
Microsoft Office I've got tens of
millions of lines of code which have
accumulated over many decades of people
at Microsoft adding more features more
features and still more features and
Microsoft tried twice to redevelop
offers from scratch and give up both
times
right so the business of managing
projects has become replaced by the task
of managing ecosystems and we now have
got various tools for doing that we've
got static analysis tools that are
things like git that enable you to
coordinate lots of people writing code
for bits of a project and then checking
it in and then you can run integration
tests and and so on and so forth and
much of the interesting work in software
engineering and the impactful work over
the past 20 years has been improving
these tools now we Face a different kind
of problem
which is how do you coordinate software
maintenance across organizations
for example a bit over a year ago we
discovered what we call the Trojan
Source vulnerability as you know some
languages like English are written left
to right and others like Urdu are
written right to left and if you're
going to have both in the same newspaper
article you need means of flipping from
left to right to right to left and these
are called bi-directional control
characters or BD characters and because
it's very complex to do you have to give
people fine-grained controls and what we
found is that if you put BD characters
into software
right you could play Havoc because you
could see to it that software would look
one way to a human developer but another
way to the computer or more accurately
to the compiler of interpreter and so
this was a vulnerability that affected
all programming languages at the same
time just about and it's also affected
machine learning systems and so we had a
fascinating experiment where we notified
the maintainers of big machine learning
systems and also the maintainers of
computer languages and of editors and
you know other tools lintos and so on
for software development that this was a
potential vulnerability because there's
a very very wide variation in response
most of the machine Learning System
people were not interested because they
don't yet have a culture you know of
patching stuff regularly and also
because it's slow and expensive to
update a large machine learning model
and the Machine learning people
considered security to be somebody
else's problem so there's a cultural
thing there as as well as a technical
thing
and among programming languages we found
that some language teams such as rust
were very keen and eager and you know
they wanted to patch instantly even
before the Public Announcement others
such as apple and Amazon didn't want to
cooperate or say anything and one then
their Oracle basically refused of
anything to do with it they said we
don't accept that this is a
vulnerability in Java it's a
vulnerability in whichever editor you
use to edit Java so this gave us an
insight into the enormously differing
cultures across the industry
towards maintenance and towards
cooperation with other firms and we also
explored the mechanisms that are
available for people to coordinate work
on a vulnerability before it's publicly
explores exposed and we find that
there's a tension for example between
what cert does because search will
enable coordination between teams
working on a pre-public bug fix on the
one hand and on the other hand companies
like hack forums which operate bug
bounties on behalf of this of the
software developers so since then we
have been trying to talk to people at
certain people at hack forums and so on
about how we can coordinate these
approaches better and this is going to
end up being a long process that lasts
many years as we get people in the
industry to coordinate the responses to
complex supply chain issues so if I were
to understand it so you're saying that
essentially it's very difficult to
actually put a number on the lifespan
because everyone is going to be treating
things differently like for some
companies like it might be better to
just kind of kill the project rather
than maintaining it whereas there might
be some other companies because of their
good engineering culture that they'll
sort of maintain the project and then
give you more support well it depends
ultimately on the company's business
model now if you've got a company that's
offering a service you know somebody
like Google or Facebook if there's a
bugger in their website you know they
have to fix it otherwise the flow of
advertising data stops and the beautiful
thing about running software on your
servers rather than your customers
phones or laptops is that you can patch
it on the Fly and so it doesn't have to
be quite as Dependable because the cost
of remediation are much lower
but of course that isn't the case for
all software and much of the software
that you see in cars cannot be upgraded
remotely you have to go to a garage and
have them reflash the memory
and in the case of Railway signals in
Britain for example are security
agencies of forbidden the remote upgrade
of Railway signal software because they
think that this is National critical
infrastructure and if the railways could
patch their software remotely then so
could the Chinese secret police and this
means that when you get a major
vulnerability that they have to send out
people in high visibility jackets to
walk up and down the tracks and change
all the software
so there are the security agencies got
in the way of
you know maintainability of Railway
signal software
and there are going to be all of these
problems again and again and again and
again now other business models the
typical business model with Indian
software companies is that you know if
someone like Tata consulting is writing
software for a client in the west the
contract will typically say that the
Indian contractor will maintain the
software for 90 days after delivery and
thereafter it's a customer's problem so
maybe there's a business opportunity for
people to offer extended maintenance
contracts the business is again
different if you have got internet of
things devices if you've got things like
room thermostats or burglar alarms or
anything like that because again many of
these are made in China and in China
because the electronics Industry is
Hardware driven maintenance is
notoriously for example in 2016 there
was a big DDOS attack from Mirai botnets
and the Mirai software well software
that's initially infected CCTV cameras
in Vietnam and in Brazil that have been
produced by these Chinese company xiaomi
and they basically built those CCTV
cameras so they could be connected to
Wi-Fi and they all had the same factory
default password and software that
couldn't be upgraded
so whenever anybody turned on one of
these devices anybody who was doing an
ipv4 scan and who could find that this
was a xiaomi camera I could take it over
and use it to DDOS people and we have
since had several hundred versions of
the Mirai worm which has been recruiting
various iot devices which had
unpatchable software with
non-vulnerabilities and this has become
such a nuisance that we now have laws in
America in Britain and in Europe which
enable the Customs people to turn back
containers full of iot software which
I've got systemic vulnerabilities you're
supposed to have different installation
passwords for each device and you're
supposed to have the ability to patch
software if something's going to go
online there are different legal tools
used for that in different countries
so this is again a world in which the
legislator is constantly playing catch
up
as selfish short-sighted Industries sell
stuff that has got vulnerabilities or
safety hazards and they don't care about
the consequences it's very interesting
because one of the episodes that we did
by another host episode 5441 on securing
software supply chain that has a
relation to what you're just saying
because one of the main things that came
out of the show was apart from the
advice that the person there was giving
on you know scanning your a code for
vulnerabilities because of the
off-the-shelf components you're using he
also talked a lot about building a
relationship with the maintainer of the
library or software that you're using so
that you could get you know better
visibility on what's happening there and
upgrade as and when they make upgrades
what do you think about that is that
good advice is that what we should be
doing
it reminds me of the comment that
Mahatma Gandhi made when he was asked
what do you think of Western
civilization and he said that would be a
nice idea
because you see one of the problems is
that the maintainers the people who have
to maintain your software can very often
fall to the business tactics of others
my classic case here is what happened
with solar winds now solar winds used to
be a great engineering company but some
very clever people set up in order to
provide software that would enable you
to optimize the performance of
complicated Windows databases in big
installations
and so it ended up being used in over a
hundred of the Fortune 500 companies and
in over a dozen American government
departments so what happened then is
that some bankers bought solar winds and
so the founders you know could then go
and buy big houses and nice yachts and
so on and the bankers went and bought up
their competitors too so that in order
to manage big Windows databases you
basically needed to use solarwinds
product
and then what happened is they sacked
most of the really able Engineers who
maintained this product and replace them
with low-cost labor from Eastern Europe
and then the Russian FSB noticed and so
they somehow managed to infiltrate
solarwinds infrastructure
and they saw to it that when solarwinds
updated its product it's included an
advanced persistent thread which
basically installed itself and reported
back to the FSB in Moscow and this meant
that over a dozen U.S government
departments were running Russian spyware
together with 100 American companies and
this was discovered only when the solar
wind software infected a security
company and they noticed
so the question here facing companies is
what sort of due diligence do you do in
your suppliers in the past you'd you'd
want to see you know the last three
years accounts from your supplier and
you'd like to see some nice PowerPoints
from them about how they planned
wonderful things blah blah blah blah
blah and now I think you have to do
slightly more ruthless and intelligent
due diligence you can't just say does
this supplier get audited by a big four
audit firm because sure they all do
that's a racket it doesn't tell you
anything you've got to ask who actually
owns this company and do they give it
toss right and if the company is
suddenly owned by a private Equity Firm
or a bank you shouldn't be running the
software anywhere critical now most
companies don't do that kind of due
diligence because it's not been part of
the business process until now
one or two companies are starting to do
it you know the clever ones but again
it's going to take time and it's going
to cost a lot of grief before people
realize that this is necessary
costs because you know if selling your
company to a private Equity Firm causes
its value to go down because 20 of your
customers will walk then as a Founder
you won't be able to realize as much
money when you sell your company
so again there will be second order
consequences third all are there
consequences all the way through the
ecosystem
I think this probably also sounds a bit
Bleak but let me ask you on how do we
mitigate these kinds of risks so one of
the things that that came out of the
previous uh show on software supply
chain attacks and probably ties in with
this obsolescence pieces also
incentivizing the maintainers would that
help incentivizing the maintainers for
giving minimum stability promise well
that's hard how do you go about defining
a service level agreement and how do you
go about incentivizing people to meet it
because it depends on the kind of
Maintenance work that's being done that
is going to vary enormously from one
type of product to another one of the
things that we have learned from the
experiment that we did with the Trojan
Source vulnerability
is that it's very very difficult if you
subcontract something like a bug Bounty
program to write a proper scope for a
contractor
to you know incentivize them to report
the right type of stuff because what
typically happened when we reported the
Trojan Source vulnerability to affirm
that used in Outsourcing a company
because the Outsourcing company would
say sorry this isn't a vulnerability go
away
this happened even when we reported to
some companies that did their own
vulnerability management because that
their own trust responders were in the
same kind of fickle the First Responders
whether in-house or outsourced had been
given a list of things that they should
treat seriously such as a remote code
execution vulnerability blah blah blah
blah blah and if you come up with
something that doesn't fall neatly
within any of these existing categories
they say sorry this is too complex for
me it makes my brain heart go away and
then the only way you can report the
vulnerability is by going to the
software maintainer you know their
customer and saying oi your guys say
that the Trojan Source doesn't affect
Google
and that you know about it already but
how come JavaScript is vulnerable right
here's our proof of concept exploit
something's wrong your mechanism is
broken please go and fix it
so with anything that's a bit off the
Beaten Track you end up having to
escalate and so again there are some
things that you can Outsource but
there'll need to be escalation
mechanisms to get around the outsourced
stuff because the scope will never be
quite right you could never have
complete contracts here safety critical
systems in particular tends to break in
unexpected ways because of combinations
of things going wrong a combination of a
software failure a hardware failure and
humans not understanding what's
happening because the stuff that you
could think of in advance you already
mitigated somehow or another
so what's the solution then would that
be like if so one of the things that
typically happens in software is that we
take an off-the-shelf component because
it's easier for us to actually build
something quicker and get something out
to the market right so the so that's the
reason why we take and then one of the
things that people usually do is check
that if it's maintained by say one of
the big companies the maintainers then
and it's got a sufficiently good rating
and you know it's got a thing that is
something that we use but then what you
do is that is it better then to build
something by yourself because of all
these risks or how do you mitigate well
that's hard if you use Microsoft as a
platform for example then to what extent
can you rely on the assurances that they
give you around windows you know there's
a nuclear power station within an hour
and a half Drive of here
which is still using Windows 95 in some
systems
right crazy but you know that's what the
world is like old systems end up being
built into safety critical stuff because
revising the safety assessment of
something like a medical accelerator or
a nuclear power station is just too
expensive so again it's difficult and
even in the case of Windows you know
Microsoft may say that Vista stops and
such and such a date but if you're a
government customer and you pay them
extra they will still give you security
updates
so there are conflicts of interest in
terms of the kind of contracts that
people want to sell and the kind of
services that other people want to buy
and ultimately I suspect the best way to
regulate this is in the application
environment
so in the case of an aircraft or a
vehicle or a or whatever you can
say I want my ship
to be maintainable for 25 years or I
want my oil refinery to keep on working
for 40 years
and then you can go and speak to the
suppliers of the various components and
you can say well what can you offer us
and often there'll be a very big gap you
know you go to someone like GE or
Honeywell or AVB and say you know what
maintenance guarantees will you give us
on these particular sensors or actuators
and they may say three euros and
thereafter a maintenance contract at a
price it will tell you at the time
so you end up with gaps that are in some
sense uninsurable
and then it is a business risk decision
by the person who is building the oil
refinery as to what they do and what
they tend to do in practice is they will
then say fine in that case we need the
refinery built so the following series
of IEEE standards and using messaging
protocols the MP3 or whatever which are
supported by three different vendors so
I can buy my sensors from ABB or GE or
Honeywell and what then happens is that
you find that you then can't change
these standards to include
authentication this is a problem that
you get for example in the world of you
know chemical plants and electricity
transmission and distribution but 20
years ago everybody started putting
devices onto IP networks because they
were cheaper than using these lines and
that meant that anybody in the world who
knew the IP address of your sensor could
read it and anybody in the world who
knew the IP address of your actuator
could operate it
and then there's been a huge big rush to
re-parametrize to put the networks in
electricity substations and all
refineries and so on into almost private
networks where there's just one Gateway
between that and the internet and the
Gateway has become very specialized and
that's where you put you know the
investment of efforts and upgrades and
so on to stop bad people getting in and
doing bad things so in a world like
control systems you can do that you can
re-parameterize but with a car it's it's
different it's difficult the typical car
nowadays has got about 10 radio
frequency interfaces
and not only does the car have its own
SIM card so it can speak to the mobile
phone network it probably connects via
Bluetooth it's probably two different
modes of radio communication with your
key fob you know for remote key entry
and for alarm deactivation you're then
going to have other radio interfaces to
the tire pressure sensors
and all of these can become attack
vectors
people have found a tax on all of them
and very often on the really boring
software that glues the radio frequency
chips to the chips that that do real
programming work from the point of view
of the car vendor so nobody's interested
in that so nobody tested it and so it's
got bugs in it so you end up in a
situation where you have to be able at
least in theory to patch all the
software in the car and that means that
you have to have the foresight to build
in the mechanisms to do that
and if you're going to do that over the
air it can better be secure otherwise
the Russians or the Chinese will do it
for you
and so what this means is that when we
graduate students with degrees in
computer science or information
engineering so that they can take the
entry-level jobs that's our emphasis or
Wipro or whatever we better teach them
this stuff and then the companies for
their part during their boot camp
training for new employees have to put
in their own cyber security training and
ongoing cyber security training so that
people remember all this stuff and they
think about it when they're working on
projects for customers
but again this becomes a big opportunity
for India because there is a significant
shortage of cyber security Workforce
worldwide and this creates an
opportunity for Indian firms to supply
that missing Talent
I think this would be a good time for me
to actually ask you something else which
struck me right now there's also this
concept of software deprecation right
which happens because you want to have
something because of a new user
requirement or things like that you just
you're upgrading now
this deprecation of software is a pretty
much similar to obsolescence I would
tend not to use these words I tend to
think in terms of software that's
embedded in systems and components and
how these systems and components work
over work and evolve over time although
somebody describes it as deprecation or
obsolescence may depend on the internal
politics of that company because you
know they may have different accounting
rules for writing stuff down but the
underlying engineering fact is that
software needs to be maintained which
may mean small tweaks here and there or
it may mean refactoring it may mean
throwing out a chunk of software and
replacing it with something different it
may mean replacing the operating system
with a newer version it may mean
replacing the web kit in your browser
with a newer version and from the point
of view of the operator outside say the
maintainer of safari that means pull out
this web kit and put it in that web kit
but from the point of view of the people
working on webkit it's a smaller update
that gets repackaged as a new version so
you see from different the point of view
of different levels in the supply chain
the nature of a change may be different
this is you know because of the way that
changes are packaged up and rolled out
so the question right now is that I
think like if you have a container with
all these different components as you
see and each one has a different end
goal for maintaining it and how it looks
and stuff like that how does so who's
the person who's owning the container
has to be very cognizant of what goes
inside the container that's what is
that's what you're saying so yeah okay
okay so this brings us to the question
of a software bill of materials right
which is the subject of a US
presidential executive order last year
and basically President Biden ordered
government agencies and contractors to
see to it that they could account for
all the software on which they were
depending right and this was a response
among other things to the solar winds
incident it's a good idea that you know
which software in your system is
critical I wasn't just solarwinds it was
log forwards which was something that
had been sitting around called software
for years but you want to know what is
compiled into the binaries on which you
rely which are some how inside your
trust perimeter in the sense that they
could break your security policy
and this is hard it's hard for technical
reasons and there may eventually be some
kind of emergent International technical
standard for how you maintain dependency
trees of stuff that gets compiled and
you'll presumably have some metadata
that goes along with binaries which
contains pointers with hash trees or
digital signatures showing everything
that went into that particular pot of
soup
and that means that if you wake up one
morning and you find that some
particular library was compromised seven
years ago by the Chinese for example you
can then just press a button and you can
see where all the places in your
organization for that library is relied
on and you can then do a cross check
against
what parts of your infrastructure are
critical in the sense that they could
bring down your operations or steal
money or kill people or whatever and you
could then prioritize a fix so this is
going to be partly Technical and partly
organizational to begin with it will be
largely organizational but I believe in
time people will develop better
technical tools that will enable you to
generate automatic records when you
build software of everything that went
into that build actually that was going
to be my question that I was going to
ask you next that should companies how
do they track this bill of material
should it be automated or do you have
hire people to do it so I think you've
kind of answered it right now that it
might start with being organizational
and then once the process is in place
you can think about automation yeah
right at the moment you have to hire
people and what's going to happen is
that the larger software companies
whether American or Indian or whatever
are then in the usual way going to write
a whole bunch of Python scripts or
whatever which will automate some of
this grant work and then eventually
people will get together at conferences
and they will try and Hammer out some
kind of international standard perhaps
the US government will you know with
luck give us academics a bunch of money
to try and facilitate that and whatever
you know this is how the industry kind
of nibs forward
after it so that's uh ankle Twisted in
the pothole like that yeah I see that
brings me up to another question this is
more project related because most of the
designers of the show are I think
practitioners one of the things that
when we are asked to come up with you
know an estimate the development costs
we never factored in this thing called
as cost of delay because of our cots
products that we use whether it's
libraries or Frameworks Etc so is this
something that we should start looking
at like when you're estimating that you
know this is going to be done by then oh
yeah we have this it's going to be done
but that's only the development costs
but then there's also this other thing
that needs to be estimated as well for
the upkeep of all our third party
dependencies well people who study
software engineering economics have
known since the 1970s since pioneering
worked by Barry Burton a little about 90
of the total cost of owning software is
maintenance and this was the case even
in the old days when people wrote their
own software and Finance on their old
men friends right because somebody like
a bank would hire some programmers to
write them a source you know software to
support ATMs when those came along then
the ATMs would be rolled out and then
over the next 20 years they keep on
wanting more features in their ATMs they
want to accept deposits they'd want to
be able to make third-party payments
they'd want to be able to buy magic
numbers to activate the prepayment
electricity measles and this meant that
you would have an ATM team of a dozen
programmers who would um it'll keep on
working away for 20 years and that ended
up costing a lot more money than the
initial development then eventually the
ATMs become Obsolete and you have to go
to a different vendor and that means
you've got to hire more people and do a
Redevelopment so you end up with this
life cycle cost an initial Sparta then
ongoing maintenance and then towards the
end of life the costs go up because you
know the software is becoming crafty
those feature interaction blah blah blah
blah blah and then you have a cut and
then you have the same thing being done
again with the next product cycle so the
maintenance costs are the delay costs
with software project failures are
something that's been around in our
industry for years and years and years
and years
it's just that if you've been working in
an Outsourcing environment for one of
the bigger the attack firms you might
not be seeing this up close and personal
because it's you know it's a pain for
your customer rather than for you but
then again it's one of the things that
drives customers to outsources in the
first place
right because you know they can
hopefully agree a project cost with an
Outsourcing firm and then the
contractors and teeth so if the
outsourcer screws up then there are
penalties to pay interesting so it's a
lot more just than the the software that
you're writing there's a lot more
happening there behind the scenes here
well yeah this is one of the things that
I try and get across to our students
that you can't see this just as a kind
of branch of Applied Mathematics where
you sit down and write the code and then
go home at five o'clock if you want to
be really good in this business if you
want to Aspire to the role of a top
technical consultant or you know a
senior manager in either a customer
company or a Outsourcing company then
you've got to understand the broader
business environment and the context in
which software has developed and you
know the history of how software
engineering as a discipline has evolved
over the past now almost 60 years
yeah one more thing I wanted to ask you
was when we spoke in the beginning we
talked a little bit about when you as
consumers we can actually demand that
there should be an easier way that when
the software that we are buying there's
an easier way for it to get patch
or to be more sustainable so in a
similar sense would it be as uh
consumers of software third-party
libraries would it be okay to ask for
the same thing as consumers of their
thing that you know you give us an easy
way to automatically patch but more
securely
Etc well consumers are simply interested
in whether their fridge is going to last
for seven years or 20 years it's the
oems who are using things like libraries
and there your choice is often between
buying some software product from a
company for money in which case you have
to very careful negotiations about
support or alternatively using an open
source project because in that case if
it breaks you know you can put your own
people into the open source developer
community and you can fix it and how the
dynamic typically has evolved over the
past 30 years or so is that you may have
a leading company a head
someone like Microsoft for example 30
years ago was trying to make all the
world dependent not just on its browser
but also on its web server
and this would mean that it would have
been able to appropriate many of the
profits from the.com boom as companies
built websites and went online and so
all the other companies which were
trying to profit from the.com boom got
together and they wrote Apache right the
companies like IBM didn't want to end up
handing over most of their profits to Mr
Microsoft and so they put a lot of the
best people on to developing Apache and
when companies like Google came along
they also contributed to that and so
this is the kind of dynamic that we have
seen in the industry that whenever
somebody threatens to monopolize two
important a part of the ecosystem there
will be a crowd-sourced open source
competitor Linux is another good example
and free PSD nobody wants to have to use
Windows all the time for everything and
pay huge amounts of money for all the
stuff that goes with the big Windows
installation interesting so I would like
to sort of go on to the next area which
is in the future Direction
so what I'm hearing from you is this is
just advice for maintainers of
repositories if you were to actually use
open source then maybe you can put
people inside and you know try and fix
problems and also the other thing what I
wanted to ask is what is the advice you
would give to people building software
so one of the things I've heard is of
course the due diligence of all your
third party the second thing is of
course you know contributing to open
source as you said and is there anything
else have I missed anything else well
the main thing that points on which many
Engineers fall down is that they don't
anticipate how long their software will
be maintained for now if you are for
example I mean one of my wife's cousins
is from India works as an engineer
designing bits and pieces for cars
things like you know controllers for
windscreen rifles and so on and if
you're designing something like that
rather than the hardware or the software
level you've got to bear in mind that
once your product ships it'll maybe be
three years in r d and it's going to be
seven years in cars that are being sold
in the showroom and then there's a
maintenance obligation for 10 years
after that that's a minimum in Europe at
the moment and it may increase over time
because of sustainability to another 10
years so you're looking at a minimum of
20 years worth of Maintenance and
possibly 30 years worth of maintenance
and then you have to ask yourself what
sort of programming language and tools
you're going to use
right now if you have been writing this
stuff
20 years ago you might have thought well
that's why it's in Java now that would
be a bad idea because now Oracle is
lagging everybody over on licensing fees
or you might have said well let's write
it in this amazing new language C plus
plus that to be honest tries to up is
promoting and people are still writing
software in C plus plus but because of
all the the Safety and Security issues
around that people are now abandoning
that and they're moving wholesale to
languages like rust and golang and
c-sharp and so on so is that what you
should be writing in are you confident
that rust is still going to be around in
30 years time these are tough decisions
and the move away from C sharp is I
think largely because of an appreciation
of the life cycle costs of doing
security patching so then a question for
researchers is this pause hidden costs
and likely future emergent costs are
there with using languages like Rustin C
sharp and what things might be around
that would help you to mitigate those
long tail costs and risks and how's all
this going to be affected by Machine
learning tools like copilot now these
are the Strategic things that you have
to think about When selecting tools
selecting development environments or if
you're an individual programmer what are
you going to invest your own time and
expertise where are you going to make
your career better
are you going to become a first class
rust programmer are you going to devote
yourself to Oracle are you going to
become a Windows fundi I mean yeah I
think it's uh interesting is I had
actually the principal research of
GitHub co-pilot I had interviewed him we
did a show on the co-pilot and one of
the things I asked him was for some of
these older languages right like
mainframes and stuff are you going to be
training the co-pilot on that because
it's becoming increasingly hard to find
people who know Cobalt and they were
thinking that yeah maybe that's
something I mean he wasn't aware but he
says yeah maybe that's something that
will be there in the future so do you
think then in that case in the case of
when you have like a smart AI powered
body would the language not matter well
the language is really going to matter
because unless you live it and breathe
it you are not going to be experts at
maintaining it that's true right the
body can help you a lot and there is
going to be a market for tools for
maintaining old stuff Micro Focus has
made huge amounts of money out of tools
to maintain all Cobalt programs that's
one of the UK software success stories
over the years and a scary story is what
happened about 10 years ago the NatWest
Bank one of Britain's big five banks
almost died because the Outsource the
maintenance of their core banking system
to affirm in India which told them that
it was expert at dealing with IBM
Mainframe assembler when it wasn't
really and are you a number of the guys
who had worked on this and had you know
been shown the door and I mean a friend
in particular had retired to live in the
deserts in Israel so he could enjoy the
sunshine and you know all of a sudden if
you went into a NatWest Bank in Britain
and said hello I've got an account here
can I withdraw some money they would say
certainly sir how much would you like
well a hundred pounds do you and they
were just handing out money to people
and get it taking a note of it because
they couldn't access the systems and
they were just hoping that they would
make it all good in the end and after
about a week or ten days they got the
systems running again but if it had been
another week you'd have had a dead bank
and out of curious the reason for this
was because the outsourced firm didn't
really know what was the problem so they
had to get exactly
so that was a nil bison experience I
think for the British economy and it's
one of the reasons that I always keep
Accounts at more than one bank because
having worked in banking I.T I I know
that sometimes you've got near misses
and I never worked for the NatWest but I
knew people who did okay I think that's
a good advice anyway for the software
Engineers listening to the show I have
to ask you two more questions before I
let you go one is of course there is
this a paper on standardization and
certification of the internet of things
which I chanced upon when I was Googling
you and that was conducted with the
support from the European Union what
motivated This research and it was quite
relevant and fascinating when I was
reading it but I just was curious to
know how did you do that well we were
approached by the European Union's
research Department which wanted a study
of what would happen to safety
regulation once you get software and
everything
you see the European Union is in effect
the world's regulator in several dozen
verticals you know from things like
medical devices through Railway signals
to children's toys and very often it's
the lead regulator because America
doesn't care and nobody else is big
enough to matter sometimes it regulates
a part of the World Market as with cars
for example there are basically car
standards for the Americas car standards
for Europe Middle East and Africa and
car standards for China right so the
cars in India for example mostly comply
with European standards and so what
happens when you get software everywhere
what happens to the regulatory agencies
in Brussels who organize and update the
safety standards to supervise the tests
that you cars have to go through and so
on and so forth is it going to be
necessary for each of these agencies to
acquire security Engineers well that
would be difficult because many of them
don't even have Engineers to begin with
they've got Loyals and economists so one
of the things we came up with was the
recommendation that the EU needed to
have an agency in Brussels to provide
the cyber security expertise for that
and the Julie passed the Cyber Security
Act which meant that the European
Network and information security agency
which had previously been located in
Greece was allowed to open an office in
Brussels so it could provide that
expertise there are other
recommendations that we made that were
accepted and others weren't accepted but
the main thing that we learned from that
was realizing that sustainability was a
real big deal this wasn't part of our
initial brief that we put into our
report the fact that hey you know you're
going to have to start thinking about
software life cycle because at present
we know how to make two types of secure
system does things like cars that were
used to test to death but then not
connect to the internet and there's
things like your phone which is secure
because it's patched every month but the
problem is your Android phone might
remain secure for a year or two because
after that the OEM won't make any
patches available of an iPhone you might
get five euros but what happens once you
start connecting your car to the
internet then if there's a vulnerability
it can be exploited remotely to cause
car crashes or whatever so suddenly you
have to start patching your car every
month or maybe every three months or
every six months but it's still a huge
additional cost who's going to regulate
that who's going to demand that software
in children's toys be capable of being
patched if a vulnerability comes along
which means for example that any bad man
anywhere in the world could phone up
your kids on the baby alarm and you know
start soliciting or whatever then
clearly you need to patch that how do
you regulate that and this is one of the
things that stood the European
commission to eventually change the
sales of goods directive so as to ensure
that everything sold in the EU the
software has to be patched for at least
two years or for longer if that's a
reasonable expectation of the consumer
and for things like fridges and washing
machine jeans and cars and so on we
already had the 10-year rule for spare
parts so that's what becomes operational
and there's now a debate going on in the
EU about whether we compel sellers of
mobile phones to patch the software for
five years in other words do we compel
Samsung to treat its customers as nicely
as Apple does
and again of course that becomes
political you know ultimately it's down
to the regulator to fix this if the
market won't fix it so standardization
and certification starts with safety it
immediately leads into security because
security vulnerabilities and safety
critical equipment become safety perform
abilities too and it immediately crosses
over to sustainability because once
you've got software there will be a
tendency for the the oems to use that
for fancy business models of you know
extracting rents from the customer by
selling mandatory subscriptions along
with it and bombarding you with ads and
so on and again that becomes abusive and
may have to be stopped by regulation
regulation to drive change or regulation
to stop change that would upset existing
Safety Stand and social expectations
social norms
this has been a great conversation and
the last question I want to ask you is
where can people reach you if they
wanted to know more about your work
would it be through email or should they
just look you up
and then try to contact the simplest
thing to do is to look up my website
okay so up to date research though you
can also download and watch the security
engineering lectures that I teach at
Cambridge it's a first-year
undergraduates and the security
engineering that I teach at Edinburgh to
fourth year undergraduates and Masters
students there's also a massively open
online course on security economics that
I developed with the University of delft
for people who are interested in the
economics of security and there's stuff
around recent policy questions for
example the attempt by the governments
in Europe and Britain and Canada and
Australia to Outlaw encryption ends to
end in messenger services like WhatsApp
great using terrorism and child safety
as excuses and we had a similar thing
here in India as well so yeah the
agencies all around the world are trying
their luck on this one think of the
terrorists think of the children give us
all your keys yeah I think in India I
think it was also talked about like I
think women's safety so I mean I I was
just called just because of my title in
my I think LinkedIn or something so yeah
so let's see where that goes yeah well
the safety of women and girls in
particular against violent crimes
extremely important but you don't fix
that problem by giving all our
photographic keys to the NSA you fix
that problem with more local policing
you fix it with child protection social
workers you fix it by changing social
attitudes towards women there's a whole
lot of very valuable work to do from
which people shouldn't be distracted by
intelligence agency attempts to get into
all our networks yeah this is great
thank you so much for coming on the show
I'll definitely put a link to your
website on our show notes and again it's
been fascinating it has really opened my
mind to a lot of things so yeah I'm
going to be doing a lot of research
after this yeah and there's also my
security engineering book oh yeah of
which there are seven chapters available
for free download okay and next year
I'll be making the whole book available
for free download oh wow wonderful it's
a very entertaining read as well I mean
it's one of the things I think the first
edition came out in 2008 if I'm not
mistaken I think yeah the first edition
was 2001. oh and the second edition 2008
so those those are both now available
free online the strategy I negotiated
with my publisher in each case is to
hold back some of the chapters from Full
public availability for a few years so
they can make some money but ultimately
I want my book to be read by everybody I
want it to be available to students not
just in you know places like Oxford and
Cambridge but also in places like you
know Bangalore and Kolkata thanks a lot
for coming on the show this is Priyanka
raghavan for software engineering radio
thanks for listening thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
[Music]
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
Channel at SC radio dot slack.com you
can also email us at team sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]